Hey, amigo.
¿Estas borracho?
Poquito.
Muy poquito.
You Quirt Evans?
Well, that depends a lot
on who's asking.
'Cause if you were
Quirt Evans...
then I'd be looking
at a dead man.
Is that right?
Well, then I'd say
a smart man would lie.
Unfortunately for you...
I'm not that smart.
[groans]
[gasps]
Grandfather!
Mister,
you all right?
John, see to
the man's horse.
This man's hurt bad.
We need to get him inside.
Come on.
You give me that horse.
Let us take care of you.
You're badly injured.
We'll take you into our house.
No! I gotta...
I gotta go.
I gotta get to
the telegraph office.
We'll take you
there.
Yeah, put him
in the corral, John.
Where that horse goes, I go.
He's a trustworthy boy.
Your horse will be safe
and well cared for.
Please.
Easy does it.
Whoa.
[groans in pain]
Sorry, folks,
we're closed down
for the night.
I know,
but it's urgent.
Can't you just--
Come out
of there, you!
I can't break schedule!
We're closed!
Can't you make an exception?
He's hurt very badly.
No, I cannot, and I don't
want some shot-up cowboy
bleeding all over my floor.
Get in here right now
and bring that light.
I'll tend to the horses.
You cannot make me
do this, sir.
send a telegraph.
Well, maybe I can't...
[cocks pistol]
but I can sure as hell
shoot you dead.
Fine. I'll do it.
But the Union Pacific
will not stand for this.
You have got
a lot of gall, mister,
coming in here in my office,
pointing a gun at me.
There,
write it down,
but I am not
gonna send it
until tomorrow.
Here.
Let me help you.
"Territorial
Recorders Office,
Fort Lansing."
[groans]
"Have found mineral claims
on plots 234 and 235.
Chart 1089."
[panting]
"Record it
in my name."
[grunts]
That's all.
And how
shall I sign it?
Quirt Evans.
Um...
perhaps we can, uh,
make some sort of...
[clears throat]
[tapping telegraph]
Okay, there you go,
Mister--
[whispers]
Is he dead?
Not yet,
but he needs help.
Wow.
Quirt Evans.
Look at his gun.
I just wanna
look at the handle
and see how many
notches he's got.
I don't know.
I can't see any,
but I sure as heck
don't want to touch it
to find out.
Wow. This is
the famous Quirt Evans.
Quite a man with
the gals, I hear.
They say that--
listen to this--
they say, "He's closed
the eyes of many a man
and opened the eyes of...
of many a woman."
I'm sorry.
Yes, could you please
get my father?
Yes.
Sir?
Sir, we need
your help.
Where are you taking him?
We're taking him home.
Quirt Evans?
Are you crazy?
I'd just as soon
have a black powder bomb
with a lit match next to it
in my house!
Is he heavy? He looks heavy.
Solid, you know?
Boy, oh boy.
I know a dozen men
who would ride
day and night
just to catch
Quirt Evans
helpless like this.
Hey, I've heard about
you people
and how you don't believe
in guns or violence
and only doing good,
but take my advice.
Stay plenty far away
from Quirt Evans.
Nothing but bad is
gonna follow this man.
Thank you very much
for your advice.
- Have it your way.
- Good night. Walk on.
[murmuring]
See ya, Quirt!
Quirt Evans.
"Ol' Quirt," I call him.
Comes by here all the time.
Old Quirt.
Friend of mine.
Does thee think
he's going to live?
I hope so.
Could thee please
bring Mother here?
Oh, and fetch
Doc Johnson, too.
[coughs]
If that doesn't quiet him,
I don't know what will.
I'll never get the bullet out
with him thrashing around
like that.
Relax, Mr. Evans,
we're just trying
to help you.
He cannot hear you.
I'm afraid to give him
any more sedative.
It might kill him.
I wonder what that delirious
mind is searching for.
He's probably
in a lot of pain.
Not with that much
laudanum in him.
It's as if he were reaching
for something specific.
By now, he should be
completely immobile.
- How is he?
- Completely delirious.
A gun?
In this house,
Thomas?
Get rid of these.
[panting and groaning]
Maybe have to get something
to tie him down.
[grunts]
- Are you crazy?
- It's empty.
[sighs]
Huh. So that's what
he wanted, his gun.
- It's sad.
- No, it's not.
It's stupid.
These wild ones,
I keep picking bullets
out of them, and for what?
Because it's
the right thing to do.
Is it?
All it does is
prolong the inevitable,
which is to wind up
in the ground,
feeding worms.
No.
Oh, that's right.
I forgot.
Never speak
any evil, right?
Now, go get some more
hot water, young lady.
Let's get this bullet
out of him.
Clint and his boys
were found dead
in the alley.
You think
this is the work
of Quirt Evans?
They still had the guns
in their hands.
Why, sometimes
I wonder.
Wonder what, dear?
Wonder if
I'll ever love
or be loved again.
A beautiful woman
with a good heart?
Any man would be lucky
to have thee.
Tell me again
how thee met Father.
[chuckles]
Again?
Thou's heard that story
a thousand times.
Oh, humor me.
It's a good one.
Well, he was...
working on the roof
of the meeting house.
He fell off.
I picked him out of the dust
and into my arms.
He always said I hugged him
before I ever knew his name.
And thou knew he was
the right man for thee
instantly.
Of course I knew.
He was a peaceful man,
a man of the Society.
An evil man would seek
a far more profitable
way of life
than being a member
of the Friends.
Still, one never knows where
or when we meet the right man.
Temperance,
the heart never lies, but...
one must be very careful.
I know how much
thee miss Joshua.
Every woman needs
a man in her life,
and Lord knows
John needs a father, but...
men like that, they...
they just aren't the type
to settle down.
Trouble follows them
everywhere they go.
He may not even make it
till the morning,
and thou hast
already judged him.
The light is in everyone.
It's thee I'm concerned about.
I just couldn't bear to see
thee lose another man,
that's all.
I know.
He's got the constitution
of a mountain lion.
He'll pull through.
Barring blood poisoning,
that is.
You can
wash him now.
He's in no danger.
These wild ones,
they always seem to
pull through just fine.
It's the godly ones
who end up dying.
You non-believers,
you always feel
compelled to question
the ways of the Lord.
I'm sorry, Thomas.
Sometimes men in my profession,
we have no other choice.
Good night, Doctor.
Thank you.
I'll be back
to check on him tomorrow.
Keep his dressings clean.
He'll be fine.
Good night.
Mrs. Whart...
get that man
out of here.
But he's very badly
wounded, Doctor.
This is not
civilized Pennsylvania.
This is the raw frontier.
You must take
a realistic attitude.
This is a town of mayhem,
theft and depravity.
Would that justify
leaving a wounded man to die?
"Build your house
by the side of the road
and be a friend to man,
ye who believe."
I don't mind
you mocking me, Doctor.
I was born
with a logical mind.
And a big heart.
You've been a good friend.
Thank you very much, Doctor.
Between the rest of
the town trying to run
all you Quakers out
and that gunslinger
upstairs,
you're going to need
your Friends.
We have
everything we need.
Good night.
I'm gonna place my bet
on the black ace.
[mumbling]
You're a shapely hussy.
[laughing]
Oh, Maggie.
Maggie, that is
just what I like.
[chuckles]
You always
knew me best.
[chuckles]
Don't stop.
Please don't stop.
[breathing heavily]
Oh, God,
I missed you.
[gasping]
[panting]
Chart... Chart 1089.
[laughs]
I found it.
Chart 1089.
We got to
call it off, Maggie.
You know I got
places to go.
I'm not
the settling down type.
I...
I used to smoke corn silk
when I was a kid.
Your hair...
your hair is just like that,
yellow and gold
all mixed up.
All gold and silky.
[sighing]
No, don't stop.
Don't stop, Maggie.
[gasps]
[click]
Hello.
You're awake.
Well, I sure hope so.
What is all this?
What?
Where am I?
Don't you remember?
Father and I helped you
to the telegraph office.
Is anything wrong?
No.
Well, the doctor says
you'll be all right
in a week or two.
You were delirious, you know,
two days and two nights.
Well, maybe that's why
I'm so hungry.
I could eat
a yearling steer.
Oh, well, we'll get you
something then.
Mother?
You talked a lot
in your delirium.
Mother, come here!
He's awake.
How is he?
Hungry.
Well, if he's hungry,
I guess he'll live.
Well, thank you much
for housing me.
Where's my horse?
John has done a fine job
of caring for your animal.
Now, would you like some
fresh smoked sausage
and eggs?
- Well, that sounds good.
- Two eggs or
would you like three?
Ma'am, I feel like
I could eat a dozen eggs
and the chicken that laid 'em.
[chuckles]
Well, then you
shall have them.
Temperance, find one
of Father's shirts
and his razor, too.
I'll make our guest
some food.
So I talked a lot, huh?
Yes. I mean,
I only listened
because I thought
you might say something
that might aid us
in helping you to...
notify your family
or wife, for instance.
What'd I say?
I mean, if you
have a wife, that is.
What did I talk about?
You, uh...
You talked about a Maggie,
how she knew you better
than anyone else.
What else?
So we can notify her,
if she's your wife.
No wife.
Hmm.
Um...
you also mentioned something
about a chart 1089.
What did I say?
[gasps]
This can go from
real friendly to real ugly
real quick.
You understand?
Why don't you lay back
before you tear out
those stitches
the doc put in you.
[grunts]
Thank you.
You're very welcome.
[sighs]
[burps]
[chuckles]
Pardon me, ma'am,
but that is one of the best
meals this old cow-puncher's
ever had.
I've never before
seen a man eat
two dozen eggs,
a pound of sausage
and half a chicken.
[Quirt]
Thank you.
I'll help thee
with the dishes, Mother.
No, no, you stay
with Mr. Evans.
Someone has to watch him,
in case he explodes.
All you folks from Pennsylvania
talk that way?
Talk like what?
"Thee."
Oh, we're Friends.
Oh, yeah?
Friends of who?
Of all.
The Society of Friends.
And some people
call us "Quakers."
- Quakers?
- It's a nickname.
Some non-members claim
we tremble before
the word of God.
Oh, I see.
So it's a religion.
Well, it's a... belief
that all life is sacred.
That on the wall there.
"Each human being
has an integrity
that can be hurt
only by the act of
that same human being
and not by the act
of another human being."
Is that Quaker stuff?
Yes.
So nobody can hurt you
but yourself?
Well, that's what
Friends believe.
So what if somebody shoots you
in the chest with a bullet,
would that hurt?
[chuckles]
Physically, yes,
but in reality,
it would really only hurt
the person doing the shooting.
Only the doer is harmed
by the evil act.
That's easy for you to say.
Are there very many
of you Quakers?
Very few.
Why am I not surprised?
[chuckles]
- [spittoon dings]
- You the telegraph man?
Certified operator, yes.
We found these
out in the street.
They belong to a fellow
named Quirt Evans.
Heard he's
a friend of yours.
Thought maybe
you could get 'em
back to him.
Just leave them here.
I'll make sure he gets them.
That Quirt,
he'd lose his shirt
if it wasn't buttoned on.
I keep telling him--
Suppose you tell me
where he's at,
and I'll get 'em
back to him myself.
Where is Quirt Evans?
You mean where is-is he?
You ever notice
how a fella starts
repeating the question
when he's either
scared to death or
lying through his teeth?
Why don't I just put a bullet
in his belly, Boss?
That'll help him quit stalling
and start remembering.
Uh, now, uh...
to be honest with you,
I hardly know the man.
Is that so?
'Cause you've been
bragging all over town
what good friends you two are.
Maybe this will
jog your memory.
Wh-What are you--
[groaning]
Great.
I look like a Quaker.
[footsteps]
I brought you up an extra--
Oh. Please
get back in bed.
The doctor said
you have to remain in bed
for at least a week.
[clears throat]
Uh...
I'm decent now,
sort of.
Sorry.
- Howdy, Quirt!
- Howdy, squirt!
[chuckles]
I see you're up.
John, that is no way
to address an elder.
Hey, we're pals now,
huh, huh?
Oh, damn it.
[grunts]
Sorry, uh...
You wouldn't want a pal
to call me "mister" now,
would you?
- Huh?
- See?
Doc Johnson told me
to let you know
that some men
over on Main Street
were looking for you.
Yeah? Who?
He said one of the men
was a Mr. Loredo Stevens.
[clicking]
Who emptied my gun?
Father.
A gun is a thing
of evil to us.
We never allow them
in our homes,
do we, John?
John, go get my pants.
John, no.
Thee tell him
to go get my pants.
Go ahead.
What?
What are you looking at?
Thee?
Thank you.
It's a good thing
I'm not a tattletale.
What's that
supposed to mean?
Oh, uh...
The... words you used.
"Thee tell him
to go get my pants,"
I think you said.
Yeah, what about it?
Well, among us,
"thee" and "thou" are used
only to address loved ones.
To others, we use
the more formal
"you" or "he."
But between mothers
and daughters and...
husbands and wives...
it's different.
People we're more...
intimate with.
I'm sorry.
Don't be.
I wish thee to...
speak to me like that.
I could take you
lots of places.
And I'd go.
Have I shocked thee?
I wouldn't say
"shocked" exactly,
but you sure do
get to the point.
As did thou.
Should I be any different?
No, Temperance.
I like you
just the way you are.
Come on out, Quirt!
We know
you're in there!
Come on out,
nobody gets hurt!
Quirt, I don't want
no innocent people
getting hurt now!
Where are my bullets?
Outside.
Mother buried them.
Come out, Quirt!
Son of a bitch.
Why don't we just
bust in?
'Cause busting through
doors with Quirt Evans
on the other side
ain't my idea
of a healthy pastime.
[knocks]
Thomas, let 'em in.
That's
far enough.
Stay in the light
where I can see you.
Howdy, Quirt.
You sure did
run rings around me,
that's for sure.
I still don't think
it was very fair, though,
the way you took
that claim from us,
especially after
me and my boys found it.
Of course,
I'm willing to listen
to your side of it.
I'm a reasonable man.
That's right.
Loredo's a reasonable
man, Quirt.
That's why he runs things
in this here territory.
So you run things in this
territory, huh, Lorado?
That's what they say.
Well, I'm pretty
new here,
so I'm just going to have
to take your word for it.
[click]
You nervous or something?
I can't figure out
why you're always
stepping on my toes.
Of course,
that is your business.
Guess I'm just a good loser.
Well, I like a good loser.
Of course, I like being
on the winning side
of any loser.
You know, I had a lot of time
to think, Quirt,
when I was trailing you
across this territory.
You were trailing me,
were you?
Mm-hmm, that burned-out
string of horses you left.
Way I figure it,
you don't really
want that claim.
Digging around in the dirt
all day.
Being a miner ain't exactly
your line of work.
Well, I don't remember it
being your line of work either.
No, no.
No, I was looking after it
for another... business partner.
Now, we don't want these
nice people getting hurt,
so I figure you wouldn't have
any problem selling it...
to me.
Well, I don't hear
anything a-jingling.
It's all right I reach
into my coat pocket?
Slow.
[heavy thud]
5,000. Gold.
Well, it's gonna
cost you 20,000.
[laughs]
Okay.
Of course, I'm gonna
have to owe you.
I don't have
the 15 on me,
but I do have the deed
right here in this pocket.
[chuckles]
Well, isn't that convenient?
Get it out.
Suppose the lovely lady there
brings us something to sign it.
Still Lorado's hired boy,
eh, Hondo?
Picking up after him,
carrying matches
for his cigar.
Go get the horses.
Yeah, you go on
and get them horses, Hondo.
Git!
[chuckles]
Take that to Mr. Evans.
That should do it.
Good to see you
up and around, Quirt.
We heard you was, uh,
flat on your back.
Sorry to disappoint you.
You just come
for that 15,000 anytime.
Anytime you feel able.
Oh, I'll feel able,
all right.
You just make sure
you hold onto it for me.
Adios.
John, saddle my horse,
please.
What do you think
would have happened
if they knew
your gun was empty?
[sighs]
Well, let's just say
it would have been
Saturday Night in Sioux City.
[coins jingle]
No, no, Quirt.
We can't accept that.
What kind of a boarder
do you think I am?
We cannot do that.
We'd tend any wounded man,
but not for pay.
Huh.
You don't believe in force,
right?
So I guess you can't force me
to take it back.
[laughing]
Thou've been
outwitted, Thomas.
[Quirt]
How long have I
been here exactly?
[Thomas]
Almost two weeks.
Huh. I kind of hate
to get going.
Must you go now?
You're still hurt.
Ma'am, your cooking
has me all healed up.
Well...
Vaya con dios, amigos.
So you're leaving?
I got places to go.
It wouldn't matter to me
where or how far.
Oh.
I see.
I thought you also
had feelings.
That's not it.
It isn't?
Well, uh...
So you feel the same way, too?
Temperance, I'm not
the kind of man who...
does these things suddenly.
So you're just not sure yet.
Sort of.
[hoofbeats approach]
He's all saddled, Quirt.
Well, then unsaddle him, son.
Does that mean that
you're gonna stay?
Loredo Stevens
owes me $15,000.
Can't very well leave
without it now, can I?
Here you go.
A double eagle?
Quirt, there's something
I'd rather have than this.
A favor, a big favor.
Well, you can
have them both,
so what is it?
Would you walk past
the schoolhouse with me?
There's a lot of boys
who don't believe
I know Quirt Evans.
[laughs]
Sure.
Everybody says that
you're the fastest gun
in the territory.
Well...
There are some people
who think I'm pretty slow.
Thank you.
[Quirt] Ain't nothing
like a Northern Chinook
to make a man feel new again.
Be sure thee help Grandfather
mind the store this morning.
There's always work
at the store to be done.
And who wants to run
the store one day?
Not anymore I don't.
Surely, thee can make it
to the store without that.
Oh. It balances me.
One leg's longer
than the other.
Thou art a liar.
Walk on.
What's that
all about, Thomas?
We're not welcome
here in this town.
Mayor Carson's trying
to make us leave.
He's trying to
run you out of town?
In so many words, yes.
I don't know
what we're gonna do.
Don't talk about this
in front of the family.
I don't want to upset them.
Well, come on.
Don't stand around.
Give us a hand.
I'm not cut out
for store work.
Fine then.
I'll do it.
No, no, no.
I'll help.
But let's just say
I'm not signing up
for full-time work.
Jonathan.
Oh, thee...
What?
Nothing.
Just thee.
Temperance,
could you get some coffee
for the storehouse?
Yes, Father.
So you're gonna
run the store
one of these days?
- I guess so.
- [chuckles]
Don't sound so excited.
Pardon me.
Who are those men?
I don't know.
Can I help
you gentlemen?
[mocking]
Can I help
you gentlemen?
Ha! We're here
to help you.
You're supposed to be gone.
- This is our home.
- Well, homes got a lot pricier.
We ain't seen no money yet.
We can't afford
what you're asking.
Is that right?
- [groans]
- [laughs]
Shut up! Your god
ain't anywhere near you.
It's all right.
Let's, uh--
Let's take a break.
Why don't you go
get yourself some hard candy
over at
the general store, huh?
Really?
You'd better get, squirt,
before I change my mind.
Nowhere,
you crazy old bumpkin.
[laughing]
Is there a problem
here, Thomas?
D-Don't you mind,
Quirt.
This doesn't involve you.
Um, Quirt Evans?
That's right, and if
you two sod-busters
got a problem with him,
well, then it's
a problem with me.
Uh, no, we got no problem
with you, Mr. Evans.
Just doing our job.
Unless your job is
to meet your maker today,
I suggest you
beat on out of here.
Let's go.
I ain't gonna get
in no gunfight
with Quirt Evans.
Well, then you're
smarter than you look.
What did those
two men want, Thomas?
They're
Mayor Carson's men.
He owns everything in this town
and wants to double our rent.
They harass all of us
constantly.
I told you, they don't want
us Quakers in their town.
I pray for Steven Carson.
You pray for him?
Carson doubles your rent,
and you pray for him?
Can't you see?
By committing his evil deeds,
the poor man
injures his soul.
It's not the man's soul
I'd be worried about.
Where are you going?
I have to see
someone.
[laughing]
♪ [saloon piano]
Well, from the looks of it,
you must be Mayor Carson.
That is me.
We don't need your kind
around here.
You just keep moving,
saddle tramp.
This town is not
a place for you.
Nice hotel.
This place must bring in
a pretty penny.
You heard me.
Vamoose.
Get out of here, or I'll have
my boys throw you out.
If by "your boys"
you're referring to
those two muskrats
standing behind me,
well...
good luck.
Carson, it's time
you lay off the Quakers.
They ain't causing
any trouble.
They ain't doing anybody
any harm, so you just
leave them alone.
Oh, yeah?
And who says so?
- Well, I say so.
- And who might you be?
Quirt Evans.
Well, anybody can come by here
and say they're Quirt Evans.
You're not known here by sight.
Anybody could say they're him.
Quirt Evans!
God, I heard
you were in town, too.
How I missed you!
You rascal,
where have you been?
- Hello, Maggie.
- Don't I even get a kiss?
- [clears throat]
- Maggie, I kind of got
some business right now.
Well, then you come down
and see me later
at the saloon.
I will do that.
Mayor Carson!
Howdy, Mrs. Whart.
We've been hoping
you'd come by to see us.
Thomas?
Thomas, come out here!
Yes, ma'am.
Here I am.
Thank you
for coming by, Steven.
All of us Quakers
are grateful to you.
Thomas. It was like I was
just telling Quirt here.
You know, things have been
going pretty well for me
over at the hotel, and...
well, quite frankly,
I don't need all that
extra money right now, so...
why don't we leave the rent
where it is.
Because I believe
that, uh,
all the people of the town
should be more friendly
to your group.
You know, be neighborly.
Mayor Carson, is that a boil
you have there on your neck?
Yes, ma'am, it is.
Have you tried
poultice of eucalyptus
to ease it?
Ma'am, I have tried
everything under the sun.
I could
lance it for you.
Uh...
Well, you're not gonna
hurt me, are you?
Oh, no, no, of course not.
You come inside.
Oh, that looks like
it must hurt awfully.
Hurts terrible,
ma'am, terrible.
Well, looks like all
your praying straightened
everything right out.
You think the gun
changed Mayor Carson?
Who says I pulled
a gun on him?
- I do.
- Well, I didn't.
Ah, well, then
he gave in more easily
than I expected.
The Lord moves
in mysterious ways,
sometimes using
very strange methods.
By strange methods,
are you referring to me?
That's right.
Well, if the good Lord's
using me to do his work,
that'd be strange,
all right.
Thomas, I cannot tell you
how much better this feels.
It's incredible!
Mayor Carson,
I'd like you to have
some of my cornbread.
It's awfully good with
your coffee in the morning.
Mmm! Makes me want
to go back to the hotel
and shoot my cook.
Well, you can always
come back for more.
We've always got plenty.
Well, thank you, ma'am.
- Goodbye.
- Bye, now.
- Goodbye, Mayor.
- Thomas.
Now, that's a real good woman,
that mother of yours.
Look at that,
she fixed my neck.
Well, if you excuse me,
I think Father wants
to give thanks.
Oh, I think
he's thanked me already.
Now I think he'd like to
give thanks to someone else.
Oh, right.
Well, I think
I've made peace
with my neighbors.
It's about time.
You know something,
I was...
I was a little worried
about coming out here
and seeing these people,
but I don't really have
a bone to pick with people
over God,
especially
when it smells like this.
I'm glad
you made me do it.
Made me feel good.
Thank you, Quirt.
You have a good day now,
Mayor.
I will, if this weather
ever lets up.
Come on, Danny,
let's go.
Let's go. Good boy.
Good boy, here we go.
Well, how bad is
dinner gonna be?
Oh, just a roast venison
and of course a skimpy
little chicken.
Well, with some
cake and some pie,
I'll try to make out.
Have you killed
a lot of people?
Stop it!
He certainly has not.
- How does thee know?
- That's enough, John.
Friends don't speak
of such things.
Shall we give thanks?
Ah, a new dress.
Yes, well, it's first day,
or as thou would call it,
Sunday.
So, will you do us
a favor?
Certainly.
Come with us.
Where to?
It's a surprise.
Whoop! Didn't mean
to scare you, ma'am.
Hello there, you old
weather-beaten hangman.
Temperance,
this is Sam O'Connell,
marshal of this territory.
How do?
John, go back in the house,
thank you.
Don't let that
gray hair fool you.
He's a curly old wolf.
I just about had you
half-hung.
Tall fellow,
good with a gun,
robbed the Baker stage,
killed a couple of folk.
Wasn't me.
He's been with us
the entire time.
I'll have to take
your word for it, ma'am,
'cause God knows
I wouldn't take his.
Oh, come on now, Sam,
you and I go way back.
When are you
and Lorado Stevens
gonna get around
to killing each other?
Loredo and I don't have
any misunderstandings.
As a matter of fact,
we just became
business partners.
Hmm. Well, either way,
I'm sure looking forward
to hanging the survivor.
I ain't got it all
figured yet.
Like, take
this fella here.
He was real good
with a peacemaker
when he was
Wyatt Earp's deputy.
But then one day,
he turns in his badge
and starts
panning for gold
on a nice little
piece of land
he laid claim on.
But out of nowhere,
he goes and sells
the claim,
and then he goes
on the prod.
Now, why? That's what
I ain't got figured.
'Cause round the same time,
a fella named Walt Enis
goes down in front of
Lorado Stevens.
Now, he was reaching
at the time,
but folks say
a gambler standing beside him
grabbed his hand.
Now, is that connected?
Only time will tell.
[patting]
How'd you stand
with Walt Enis?
I knew him.
Do you think...
they're connected?
I know a lot of people.
Ah, well...
I'll figure it.
I always do.
I'm patient.
Sometimes things connect.
Sometimes they don't.
But don't be looking at him
with your eyes all bugged out
like a cowbird's
because there ain't
no future in it.
So long, Quirt.
Make sure you keep
a lot of leather wrapped
around your hog leg
when you're in my town.
Stay away from
Lorado Stevens.
He owes me money.
Who knows?
I might come out on top.
That would be worse.
Worse?
It'd be worse if I go down
than if he goes down?
- Of course, then--
- Oh, right.
Then I'd be the one
with the marred soul.
It'd be worse
that I couldn't love thee.
All right.
I won't look up Lorado.
Quirt?
Whoa.
I thought
that was you.
Randy.
Uh, Mr. And Mrs. Whart,
this is Randy McCall.
How do you do?
Well, well, well.
And how do you do?
Just fine, thank you.
- Well, well, well.
- You said that before.
Don't let us keep you
if you're in a hurry.
I'm in no hurry.
I ain't got no place to go.
Well, we do.
You could come along
with us if you like.
That would be nice. Where?
To meeting.
- To meeting?
Yes, to meeting.
You don't want
to go, do you?
It would be nice
if you could.
We'd be happy to have
any friend of Mr. Evans.
You would?
Well, that'd be fine.
You know, ma'am,
I sure am an old friend
of Quirt's.
Matter of fact,
I remember a time
we were chasing some cattle
down by the Lano River,
and old Quirt here,
when the herd
started to stampede,
he pulled me out
from underneath them.
Then there was another time
down at Opoe's Palace
in San Antone--
[clears throat]
We're late.
I was just trying to--
Goodbye.
You could join us later.
It's just on
the other side of town.
Thank you, ma'am.
Walk on.
[bell tolls]
Friends, as we all know,
the purpose of this meeting
is threefold.
We're trying to raise money
for a new meeting house.
As always, to give thanks
for the goodness that is
bestowed upon us.
But also to give thanks
that we are now going
to be able to settle down
here in this town.
Quirt, please,
come up here.
We are happy to present you
with this token of
our friendship for you.
This is Quirt Evans.
It's because of him that
we're gonna be allowed to stay.
It provides us
with another instance
that shows us
that all men are good
if they are
shown the light.
He persuaded Steven Carson
to let us stay.
May I shake your hand,
Quirt Evans?
May I shake
your hand?
It was nothing.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Appreciate it.
Quirt.
- God bless.
- May the Lord bless you.
Come on.
[Quirt]
Take this Bible.
Let's get out of here.
- A Bible?
- Come on, Randy.
Oh, brother,
this is good readin'.
Well, then you can keep it.
Just keep moving.
Oh. All right.
This sure is a book
I'm gonna read.
- I didn't know you could read.
- Listen to this.
"Benanaya,
the son of Jahodia,
slew two men of Moab
and killed three lions."
- You ready for a drink, Randy?
- You bet I am.
Just like old times,
eh, Quirt?
This here wine
may be fancier than whiskey,
but it sure don't give
quick action.
Well, to tell you
the honest truth,
I don't even like it.
[giggles]
But it is sure
fashionable.
How do you like it,
Maggie?
It tickles down,
and it's expensive,
so I like it.
- You sleepy, tall man?
- Nope.
Worried?
Or maybe just plain bored?
Not a chance, baby.
You can never bore me.
Well, I wish I had that
in writing.
You know,
it's been a long time
since you told me
how my hair reminds you
of corn silk.
All right.
Your hair reminds me
of corn silk.
All gold and silky?
That's right,
all gold and silky.
You've changed.
You're less romantic.
You're far away,
distant.
What happened to you
out there?
- There was this--
- [clears throat]
Take a turn at the wheel.
Win yourself a farm in Kansas.
I don't want
a farm in Kansas.
All right then.
I'll win you a trip
around the world.
Miss Maggie,
customers are waiting.
That's no way
to treat customers.
Give me a stack of blues.
♪ You're not the man
that I once knew ♪
♪ There's something different
about you ♪
♪ The sparkle in your eyes
is strange ♪
♪ Your style, your walk
your look has changed ♪
♪ You used to smile
when you came near ♪
♪ And whisper sweet things
in my ear ♪
♪ We couldn't bear
to be apart ♪
♪ Now someone else
has gotten your heart ♪
♪ I want you still
I can't deny ♪
♪ I long for you
when you pass by ♪
♪ But something's different
about you ♪
♪ You're not the man
that I once knew ♪
that I ♪
♪ Once knew
[applause]
17 black!
That's it.
I've lost my buttons
on my shirt.
Cash me out.
Bourbon, tall glass.
There's no need for
barrelling through here
like that, friend.
I interrupt something?
You interrupted a very
important conversation
between me and my brothers.
Gentlemen! Gentlemen,
no trouble, please.
Just got this place
put back together.
If I think what's about
to happen happens,
it's gonna round out
a full day.
Maggie.
That was beautiful.
There's your trip.
What's eating you, tall man?
Did you have words
with them Baker brothers?
Who?
Those three rattlesnakes
at the bar.
No.
'Cause I heard
they like to cause trouble.
Well, then maybe I should
go apologize.
More whiskey.
That's it.
I'll be right back, I hope.
Randy, where the heck
you been?
Gentlemen, gentlemen,
stop this foolishness, please!
You don't know
what you're doing to me!
I've got a family!
Get him, Randy!
Oh! You get him,
you big lout!
What are you doing, Randy?
I'm sorry, Quirt.
- Stop!
- Let's get out of here.
Count 'em
as we throw 'em out.
- [punch]
- [screaming]
That's one!
Stop counting.
Ah!
Oh, honey.
I was so afraid
you were gonna
get hurt.
Have a drink.
Nice dance.
We got money, we got whiskey,
we got lovely ladies.
We just had
a beautiful fight.
I tell you,
we got to count
our blessings.
You been reading
that Bible again.
[Maggie]
Now, that's something
I thought I'd never see.
What?
A Bible with
your name on it.
Here you go, honey.
Oh, thank you.
[Maggie]
Now, tell me something.
What's that, Miss Maggie?
Where on earth
would you get a Bible?
Randy, stop him!
With what?
Where's he going?
Has he forgotten
something?
[giggling]
No.
We thought you had gone.
So did I.
What happened to you?
[sighs]
I've been drinking
that demon alcohol again.
Come back with us.
That's all you need
is me as a boarder again.
You're always
welcome in our home.
Thomas, would you
give me a hand with
those barrels out front?
Yeah.
So you came back.
I had to. I just wanted
to see your face again.
Why?
I don't know exactly.
Why did you go away
without saying anything?
[sighs]
I don't know that
exactly either.
I think it's because
I scared you away.
I know it sounds strange
that I could scare you,
but I mean it.
I think you thought that...
living with me would become
tiresome and dull
after a while.
Hush now.
I'm not such a fool,
you know.
I had a very kind man
who was very good to me.
And I also know there are
people that fall in love
and stay together,
and there are people
that fall in love and don't.
I know you're
afraid that...
I'd tie myself
around your neck,
and after you got tired
of having me,
you wouldn't be able
to get rid of me.
So I made up my mind
that if you came back,
I would tell you this--
that whatever you want,
that's the way
it will be.
If I go away,
you'll come with me?
If I go away, you and John
would come with me?
[rooster crowing]
Now, there's something
I never thought I'd see.
Quirt Evans
doing honest work.
Your horse is
as quiet as you are.
I taught him.
But I reckon you would've heard
if you wasn't working so hard.
Haven't you got some
real law work to do
someplace else?
[chuckles]
Yeah.
I just like to keep track
on your whereabouts.
You know, Quirt...
I always figured on using
a new rope when I hang you
'cause I kind of
respected you.
Mind your own
business.
I'm trying.
It's a shame how
things don't turn out
the way they should, huh?
Take that young lady there.
What she should have
is a nice young man
that knows how
to treat her right,
who's gonna give her
the things that she deserves
and not leave her with
a legacy of pain and deceit.
Well, things aren't
always what they seem,
so why don't you
just move on and
leave us alone?
Someone that she would
always know where he was,
who could give her
a home, family--
Don't make me angry,
Sam.
Marshal or not,
I'll run your ass off.
I ain't never been
run off nowhere.
I want to stay, I stay.
Thing is,
I gotta get going.
You know, Quirt,
you don't rate a new rope
with me.
Look, Temperance, uh...
I've been kicking around
a long time.
I've got a checkered past.
But could a woman
like you accept me
for who I am,
for what I am?
I love thee.
Did thou accept me?
Want to come
into town with me?
I'm going to...
pick up something from
the storehouse for Father.
Love to.
All right, you win.
[sighs]
Now I know why I don't like
being a store clerk.
It's too much work.
Quirt Evans.
Yes, ma'am.
I've never said that
aloud before.
I like the way
it sounds.
Where'd you get
such a name?
Well...
the man who
half-raised me
gave it to me.
My folks were
killed by Indians.
His name was Walt Enis.
He was downed
in a gambling place.
He was murdered.
It's getting late.
We should be heading back.
♪
[man]
He ain't strapped.
I don't see no gun.
[Lorado]
Just 'cause you don't see it
don't mean it ain't there.
Go!
Stay away from the door.
Please, this won't be
solved with violence.
Temperance, I don't expect
these men are here
to pray with me.
Come on out, Quirt!
Just you and me this time!
Fair fight!
Right here, right now!
You call
trying to ambush me
a fair fight?
Light 'em up.
Burn 'em out like
a couple of prairie dogs.
Think about the woman, Quirt!
Temperance, look out!
Quirt!
[coughing]
Nobody'd survive
a fire like that.
Nobody's getting
out of that alive.
I need to see a body.
If he's dead,
I want to see it.
The way that
fire's blazing,
ain't gonna be nothing left,
except maybe a gold tooth.
Hmph! That there fire
would melt gold.
We're out of whiskey
then, boys.
Drinks are on me.
Let's warm our bellies
at the bar.
Feels like this Chinook's
coming to an end.
[coughing]
Thomas, get that doctor!
And watch the front
and back of the house!
Dr. Johnson
will sit with her
through the night.
All we can do now
is pray
and wait for
this storm to pass.
How is she?
Drink?
It's amazing, the varied uses
to which men put alcohol.
For each different
individual,
it's either a stimulant,
a depressant,
or an anodyne.
Presently, I am employing it
as an anodyne.
Get to the point.
The practice of medicine
is one of the most
infuriating professions
that have been known to man.
Takes 30 years of practice
to discover that,
in the final analysis,
there's nothing you can do
but stand back and watch.
If she has a lucid moment,
you'd better speak to her.
I'm not trying to argue you
out of anything,
but maybe you should stop
and think.
She wouldn't like this, Quirt.
I'm not arguing for or
against her point of view,
but I know that, to her,
the world's worst tragedy
would be that
you should kill a man.
Of course,
you could argue logically
whether she would know
if you killed him or not, but...
[sighs]
I think...
I think she would know.
Any discussion has to have
at least two participants.
Of course, if you refuse
to answer me--
Quirt, wait!
Don't do this!
Come back!
I'm sorry, Thomas.
I hate to
tell you this, but...
I think we're about to
see a perfect example
of "an eye for an eye."
Temperance! Temperance,
what are you doing
out of bed?
Thou art very ill, dear.
We must stop him.
If you don't stay in bed,
young lady...
Her fever's down.
I don't know if I
believe in miracles,
but this is one lucky
little lady.
He needs us, Father.
Mother.
Yeah, Lorado gave me
this beating. Look at that.
Wait'll Quirt
hears about this.
Boy, oh, boy.
He will have something
to say about it,
believe you me.
Why, I wouldn't be
surprised if Mister--
Mr. Evans?
You know Lorado Stevens?
Yes, sir, I do.
He's in the saloon
with dirt-buster Hondo, sir.
You're going
to take him a message.
Let's drink a toast...
to the late Quirt Evans.
I wouldn't
get excited just yet.
Please, gentlemen,
I don't want
any more trouble.
I'm-- I'm just
carrying a message.
Yeah?
He's waiting.
And who would that be?
Quirt Evans.
Oh, hell.
I'm gonna kill that pilgrim
for sure this time.
He also wants me to buy you
a bottle of whiskey.
For what?
Says you're gonna need
to drink at least
half the bottle
to get up the nerve
to come outside.
You want me to kill
this here tenderfoot
just to get warmed up, Boss?
Easy, Hondo.
You keep your money, mister.
I'll be back in here
in one minute,
and you can
buy us all a drink.
Whoa. Quirt!
Quirt!
Temperance...
Killing you's gonna be
real easy, just like
it was killing Enis.
He got drunk,
shot his mouth off.
How else
would I have known
about that claim?
[click]
Ain't much dignity in killing
an unarmed man, Lorado.
I wouldn't expect even you
to stoop that low.
Watch me stoop.
[Marshal]
Nothing ever
turns out right.
I was onto them
from the beginning.
They robbed the stage
and committed a slew
of other crimes,
but if you had have
downed them,
I'd have had to hang you.
Things don't ever turn out
the way they should.
But I'm still here.
You just keep on
with your old ways.
It's only a matter of time
till I hang you.
Not me, Marshal.
Oh, yeah?
That's right.
Then I guess you don't care
about that mineral claim
you wired into
the land office
at Fort Lansing
a little while back.
What are you talking about?
Well...
now that Lorado
don't own that deed,
and since you were forced
to sign under suspicious
circumstances,
I reckon that you are
probably the rightful owner
of that property now.
You don't say.
I do say.
I reckon you're
a very rich man, Quirt Evans.
You don't say.
You'll be able to look after
that lovely lady of yours
and her family.
Well, it just
goes to figure, don't it?
What's that?
The day I become
the richest man in Oregon
is the day
I don't need it anymore.
Yeah.